# **Apostolos Kalatzis**

903 Peter Koch Tower, Apt 903, Bozeman, Montana 59715, USA apostoloskalatzis@yahoo.com • +1 (714) 801-5190

I am a Ph.D. student at the Gianforte School of Computing with training in computational physiology, machine learning, robotics, and human factors. My research involves human subjects, wearable technology and the design of machine learning models to better augment human cognition in Human-Computer, and Human-Robot interactions.

#### **EDUCATION**

#### Montana State University, Bozeman, Montana, USA

■ Ph.D. in Computer Science

Aug 2019- Present

- Advisor: Dr. Laura Stanley
- · Focus: Human-Computer Interaction, Human-Robot Interaction, Affective Computing, Cognitive Workload

#### California State University, Los Angeles, Los Angeles, California, USA

• M.Sc. in Computer Science

Aug 2016 – May 2019

- Advisor: Dr. Mohammad Pourhomayoun
- · Focus: Machine Learning, Dimension Reduction.
- Cumulative GPA: 3.7 / 4.00

# University of West Attica, Athens, Greece

■ B.S. in Computer Engineering

Feb 2009 - Sep 2014

- Supervisor: Prof. Michael Glabedakis
- Thesis: Executive Construction, Equipment Design, Functional and safety specifications of Police Criminal Investigation Department.

# RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

# Montana State University, Bozeman, PI: Dr. Laura Stanley

Aug 2019 – Present

- NSF Grant (AMELIA): Student lead at Montana State University Bozeman
- Developed affective recognition models for predicting clam and stress states in VR
- Developed machine learning models for cognitive workload recognition
- · Developed methods for personalizing human-system interactions using a two-Layer multimodal approach
- Designed methods and machine learning models for real time Cognitive Workload recognition and robot adaptation in Human-Robot Collaboration
- Monitored Task Performance and Situational Awareness in Human-Robot Collaboration Under Varying Levels of Cognitive Workload and User Interface Information Exchange

#### California State University, Los Angeles, PI: Dr. Mohammad Pourhomayoun Jan 2018 – May 2019

- Supervisors: Prof. Mohammad Pourhomayoun
- Thesis: Interactive Dimensionality Reduction in Remote Health Monitoring system.
- · Designed advanced algorithms based on machine learning for monitoring patients with chronic diseases
- Created advanced data analytics methods to predict health conditions and providing clinical interventions with the goal
  of preventing medically adverse events.

# **PUBLICATIONS**

#### .33tocPEER REVIEW CONFERENCE PAPERS

- [1] Apostolos Kalatzis, Ashish Teotia, Vishnunarayan G. Prabhu, and Laura Stanley. "Classifying Affective States in Virtual Reality Environments Using Electrocardiogram and Respirational Signals." In 2021 IEEE International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Virtual Reality (AIVR), 2021.
- [2] Saidur Rahman, Apostolos Kalatzis, Mike Wittie, Ahmed Elmokashfi, Laura Stanley, Stacy Patterson, David L Millman. "Short and Sweet Checkpoints for C-RAN MEC." *In 2021 IEEE Cloud Summit (Cloud Summit)*, 2021.
- [3] Apostolos Kalatzis, Ashish Teotia, Vishnunarayan G. Prabhu, and Laura Stanley. "A Database for Cognitive Workload Classification using Electrocardiogram and Respiration Signal." *In International Conference on Applied Human Factors and Ergonomics*, 2021.
- [4] Apostolos Kalatzis, Laura Stanley, Rohith Karthikeyan, and Ranjana K. Mehta. "Mental stress classification during a motor task in older adults using an artificial neural network." *In Adjunct Proceedings of the 2020 ACM International Joint Conference on Pervasive and Ubiquitous Computing and Proceedings of the 2020 ACM International Symposium on Wearable Computers*, 2020.
- [5] Apostolos Kalatzis, Mohammad Vahedi, and Mohammad Pourhomayoun. "Interactive Learning for Data Acquisition in Remote Health Monitoring." *In Proceedings of 2019 NASA Direct STEM Annual Symposium*, California State University, Los Angeles, California, USA, 2019.

- [6] Apostolos Kalatzis, Bobak Mortazavi, and Mohammad Pourhomayoun. "Interactive Dimensionality Reduction for Improving Patient Adherence in Remote Health Monitoring." *In Proceedings of 5th Annual Conference on Computational Science and Computational Intelligence*, Las Vegas, Nevada, USA, 2018.
- [7] Yoo SangSeo, Apostolos Kalatzis, Navid Amini, Zilong Ye, and Mohammad Pourhomayoun. "Interactive Predictive Analytics for Enhancing Patient Adherence in Remote Health Monitoring." In the 8th ACM MobiHoc2018 Workshop on Pervasive Wireless Healthcare, Los Angeles, California, USA, 2018.

#### UNDER REVIEW

- [1] Apostolos Kalatzis, Vishnunarayan G. Prabhu, Saidur Rahman, Mike Wittie and Laura Stanley. "Emotions Matter: Towards Personalizing Human-System Interactions Using a Two-Layer Multimodal Approach." *In Proceedings of the 2022 ICMI Conference on Multimodal Interaction*, 2022.
- [2] Apostolos Kalatzis, Sarah Hopko, Ranjana K. Mehta, Mike P. Wittie and Laura Stanley. "Sex Parity in Cognitive Fatigue Model Development for Effective Human-Robot Collaboration." *IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters*, 2022.

#### IN PREPERATION

- [1] Apostolos Kalatzis, Saidur Rahman, Mike Wittie and Laura Stanley. "Task Performance and Situational Awareness in Human-Robot Collaboration Under Varying Levels of Cognitive Workload and User Interface Information Exchange." *IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters*, 2022.
- [2] Apostolos Kalatzis, Saidur Rahman, Mike Wittie, and Laura Stanley. "Real time Cognitive Workload Recognition and Robot Adaptation in Human-Robot Collaboration." *Journal of Human-Robot Interaction*, 2022.
- [3] Apostolos Kalatzis, Connor Markus, Mike Wittie, and Laura Stanley. "Vision Assistant in Mixed Reality to Improve Human Robot Collaboration" *In Proceedings of the 2023 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems*, 2023.

# TALKS AND PRESENTATIONS

Classifying Affective States in Virtual Reality Environments Using Electrocardiogram and Respirational Signals. *IEEE International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Virtual Reality (AIVR)*. 2021

A Database for Cognitive Workload Classification using Electrocardiogram and Respiration Signal. *In International Conference on Applied Human Factors and Ergonomics* 2021

AI/ML in UX Design. Montana State University

2021

Mental stress classification during a motor task in older adults using an artificial neural network. *In the* 2020 ACM International Joint Conference on Pervasive and Ubiquitous Computing and Proceedings of the 2020 ACM International Symposium on Wearable Computers 2020

Interactive Dimensionality Reduction for Improving Patient Adherence in Remote Health Monitoring. 5th Annual Conference on Computational Science and Computational Intelligence 2018

Interactive Predictive Analytics for Enhancing Patient Adherence in Remote Health Monitoring." *iN the 8th ACM MobiHoc2018 Workshop on Pervasive Wireless Healthcare* 2018

# RESEARCH GRANTS

National Science Foundation 2028972: An Artificial Intelligence-Inspired Computing Application for Detecting the Early Onset of Pneumonia \$255,315 - **Principal Investigator** 

#### **AWARDS**

 Meritorious Award, Montana State University Outstanding new doctoral student. 2019

Recognition for actively engaging in Research, California State University, Los Angeles

2019

Undergraduate Researcher Award, University of West Attica

2011

# PRESS AND NEWS COVERAGE

### PRESS AND NEWS Montana State University News Service

MSU graduate student on frontier of adapting robots to work better with humans

Montana State University News Service

MSU researchers win \$1.2 million grant to improve worker-robot interaction

ABC FOX Montana

MSU students study robotics to improve workforce

# PROFESSIONAL AFFILIATIONS & ACTIVITIES

Joint Honor Society,

Los Angeles, California, USA

Member 2018 - Present 2000 - Present

### **Greek Traditional Dances**

### **TEACHING EXPERIENCE**

#### **Graduate Teaching Assistant**, Montana State University

• Social and Ethical Issues in Computer Science

Fall 2019

- · Assisted head faculty member with classroom instruction material, exams, and record keeping.
- Lead, supervised, and planned recitations.
- Managed course content through online Learning Management Systems.

# **Graduate Teaching Assistant**, California State University, Los Angeles

Advance Machine Learning, Advance Topics in Data Science

Spring 2019

- Assisted head faculty member with classroom instruction material, exams, and record keeping.
- Lead, supervised, and planned Labs.
- Managed course content through online Learning Management Systems.

# OTHER WORK **EXPERIENCE**

# AB Vasilopoulos, Vonitsa, Aitoloakarnania, Greece

System Administrator

Nov 2015 - Jul 2016

- Configured, tested and maintained network equipment.
- Planned and implemented upgrades to System hardware and software.
- Maintained and monitored the server room, the wireless Network and other server infrastructure.

# Vonitsa City Hall, Vonitsa, Aitoloakarnania, Greece

Software Engineer Intern

Sep 2011 – Aug 2012

- · Provided continued maintenance and development of bug fixes and patch sets for existing web applications.
- Performed all testing and troubleshooting methods and documented resolutions in the system.
- Wrote test cases so that the applications could be tested in a legitimate environment.

#### **OUTREACH**

# What is Computer Science

- Harding high school
- West Yellowstone high school

#### **SERVICE**

#### Organizer

- Montana State University Department of Computer Science prospective student visit day spring 2020
- MSU Department of Computer Science new graduate student orientation fall 2020

#### **MENTORING**

#### Mentored 3 Undergraduate students over a span of 3 years leading an NSF Project

 Connor Marcus 2021- Present

· Now Sophomore in Computer Science

2020-2022 Kajia Coziar

Now graduate student in Computer Science at Montana State University-Bozeman

2019-2021 Michael Wetherbee

· Now cloud engineer at FDM Group

### REFERENCES

# ■ **Professor Laura Stanley** Montana State University

Barnard Hall 352, Bozeman, Montana 59717, USA laura.stanley@montana.edu • +1 (406) 994-4149

### Professor Mohammad Pourhomayoun

California State University, Los Angeles 5151 State University Drive, Los Angeles, CA 90032 mpourho@calstatela.edu • +1 (323) 343-6688